Great storytelling is making people feel
the idea, not just understand it. I've
sat in rooms with some of the most
brilliant minds on the planet. And I
noticed something. [music] There are
certain speakers where the audience
listens to them, might applause, [music]
and then forgets what they say. And then
there are certain speakers that the
audience is moved sometimes to tears,
standing ovation, and when they walk out
of that room, even years later, they
remember what the [music] speaker said.
What is the difference between these two
type of speakers? It has to do with the
emotion they bring into their
storytelling. There's a [music]
five-step framework that I'd like to
teach you, and this five-step framework
is going to make anything you choose to
communicate [music] absolutely
unforgettable.
The ability to tell a story is one of
the most amazing meta skills you can
learn. It transforms so many things
about you. From the way you talk about
your company to the way you command
respect from stage to the way you're
able to connect with people in a room on
a date or even to entertain your kids
that most people get storytelling wrong.
What I'm going to show you in this video
is how to become such a masterful
storyteller that doors open for you. And
before I begin, let me first tell you
who I am and why you want to be
listening to this video. If you are
looking to improve your ability to speak
and your ability to communicate, my name
is Vish Lakani. I'm the founder of Mind
Valley and for 22 years I have created
many of the bestselling personal growth
and wellness programs in the world.
Combined the programs I produce with
people like Jim Quick, Marissa Pier,
Dave Aspbury, May Musk have sold half a
billion dollar worth of content. And
most of this came true. Storytelling.
Not only have I used storytelling to
build one of the most successful
personal growth apps in the world. Our
app has been featured in every single
Apple store last year, but I also used
it to write this book, The Code of the
Extraordinary Minds. And this book
became the number one book in the world.
Why? because of the unique storytelling
technique I'm about to share with you
and how I applied that technique to the
first 20 pages of this book that caused
the book to have one of the stickiest
open rates. So, while most people pick
up a book on Kindle and put it down
after they browse through it, this book
you could not put it down because of the
technique I shared here. Now, you're
going to want to grab a pen and paper
and you're going to want to pay
attention because we're going to go
fast. I'm going to give you examples.
I'm going to cover five things and they
spell out HSS.
Okay. Now, I've created a little
sentence to help you remember these five
things and we're going to go bit by bit
and it says, "Heroes start their stories
somewhere." So, repeat after me. Heroes
start their stories somewhere. H STSS.
This are the five things that you can
use to turn any ordinary story into
something unforgettable. But let's go a
little bit further. For those of you who
want to get a little bit edgy, this is
how my students remember it. Holy
that's so smart. Much easier, right?
Holy that's so smart. And by the
way, guys, that is what your audience is
going to be saying about your ideas when
you apply this technique. So, are you
ready? H S T SS. Now, we're going to
start with the hook. So, the hook is how
you capture the person's attention and
leave them hanging. My story started
with this simple hook. I was about to
get on stage in Calgary in 2009 with the
Dalai Lama and I was so unbelievably
nervous. While about to get on stage
with this holy man, this world
visionary, I decided to pop into the
hotel bar in the middle of the day and
asked for two shots of vodka. And the
story goes on to explain and describe in
vivid detail me by the bar sweating,
nervous, pounding back shots of vodka
before going on the stage with a global
religious leader. Now, that was a hook.
Now, why was it a hook? Because great
hooks collide facts. That story kept
people reading past page 11. Why?
Because, well, you want to know what
happened next. Did I pass out drunk? Did
I embarrass myself in front of the Dalai
Lama? That was a powerful hook. But
there's another reason that story work
and I want you to write this down if you
happen to have a pen and paper. It's
called idea collision. You take two
fundamentally different ideas and you
smash them together. What were the two
fundamentally different ideas here?
Religious leader and shots of vodka. The
human mind is not used to hearing both
these ideas in the same sentence. This
makes it a hook. Great speakers start
their talks with a hook that arouses
curiosity, captures the attention of the
room, and frequently one of the most
powerful ways to capture that attention
is the idea collision. Now, when you're
telling a story on social media, the
hook has to be incredibly tight, 3
seconds. I remember sitting down and
interviewing the great social media
superstar Jay Shetty. Jay said the first
3 seconds hook them and then all the way
up to second 11 go deeper in the hook.
That's when you start the story. So on
social media I might start this story in
the following way. I can't believe the
Dalai Lama made me kick back shots of
vodka. That's the first 3 seconds. Now
that is the hook. You want to understand
the Dalai Lama made you kick back shots
of vodka. And then I go on to the rest
of the story. So what happened was I was
invited to share the stage with the
Dalai Lama when she was visiting
Calgary. But I was so absolutely
nervous. I ran into the hotel bar and I
started kicking back shots of vodka.
This is what happened next. That's 11
seconds. Now you have a hook with an
idea collision optimized for social
media. Powerful, isn't it? Now here's
the thing. You can apply the same thing
to a stage talk. You can apply the same
thing to a presentation. When you're
giving a presentation, you have a
captive audience because you have people
in a room. You have a little bit more
time to establish your hook. And this is
what I'm going to teach you to do. Now,
you can even do this on an interview.
Just 2 days ago, I was on stage at a
conference here in London and I was
asked to interview the billionaire
Naveen J. And Naveen said something
really interesting that captivated the
entire audience. He was speaking about
raising genius kids. Okay? And Naveen's
kids are all super successful
entrepreneurs. And people often ask him,
"How do you raise children who are that
successful?" I mean, his son is Uncle
Jane, one of the youngest billionaires
in America. So, Naveen said, "This is
how I raise kids who are
entrepreneurial. I don't buy the
that I need to spend all my
free time with my kids." This was the
hook. Now, notice what he did. Idea
collision. But he's about to go further.
He goes on to say, "I make my kids see
me working." Why is this an idea
collision? Because as parents, and I'm a
parent, we are told when your kids are
around you, don't worry. Be attentive to
them. Focus on them. Naveen, whether you
agree or not, he created an idea
collision. He goes on to explain and
craft the story. He says, "When my kids
wake up on Sunday morning and they come
to the living room, I'm not sitting in
front of the TV. I'm not reading a book.
I'm on my laptop working. They see me
working late at night. They see how
passionate I am for my job." Your kids
see you in front of the TV before they
go to school. They come back from
school. They see you in front of the TV.
What mental model do the children get?
The mental model is my parents love
watching TV. I'm going to grow up and
love sitting in front of the TV. But my
kids, they see me working. What mental
model do they get? That work can be
meaningful. That work can be passion.
That your work can be so enjoyable that
even on a Sunday morning, you want to
work with a smile on your face. Okay.
Now, you don't have to agree with what
Nadine said, but you got to admit he
captivated that audience. Not everyone
agreed with him but by creating the idea
collision he made his point. That's why
he is frequently asked to come on stage
and do interviews because he has a hook
for almost every interview question he
knows he's going to be asked. So that is
the hook that there is a second part to
ideas and the second part is stakes.
Now, I've already given you a clue for
the second part for the stakes concept.
In a movie, the stakes are the
opportunity where the hero might fail.
You see this in all the great movies
when Luke Skywalker has his hand cut off
by Darth Vader. When in Avengers, Thanos
makes his snap and half the people of
the planet disappear, including half the
superheroes, gone for good. These are
the stakes. It's the moment when
everything might collapse, when
everything might end. Human beings pay
attention to stakes. Maybe it's a
biological wiring. Maybe we need to pay
attention when we hear stories of
tragedy, of chaos, of surrender because
we need to get the lesson so we can get
out of the same situation. So stakes
grip our mind. And this is how you use
it in a story. Now, there's another
reason that stakes help you connect with
an audience. Stakes bring in humility.
Stakes bring in humbleness. Stakes talk
about the danger, the surrender, the
chaos that you were facing in your life.
It makes you relatable. Great
storytellers bring themselves to connect
with the audience. Now, I started this
talk by telling you about my book being
number one in the world. There was a
reason for that. When you're on YouTube,
you have so many videos to watch. I need
to establish my credibility because you
may not know who I am, but now that I've
established my credibility, I need to
show you my failure. I need to show you
where I started from. That makes me and
you relatable. So, when I'm telling the
story of how I started my company, Mind
Valley, I always go into the stakes. And
this is the story I tell. I want you to
observe this story and observe how I
tell the story because you're going to
see the stakes. And then you're also
going to see point number three and
point number four, how everything lines
up perfectly. The story goes like this.
So I graduated from University of
Michigan, you know, barely passing
grades, but I got the degree I always
wanted. It was 1999 and I came out with
a computer science degree. I moved to
Silicon Valley and I had this great
dream to start this software uh that I
had invented. But I needed some money to
get started. So I went to my dad and I
borrowed $30,000 from my dad and I
promised him I would pay him back. And I
loved my dad and I knew he loved me and
I knew this 30 grand that he lent me was
a lot for him. Now I moved to Silicon
Valley but folks my timing sucked. The
dot bubble burst just shortly after I
landed in Mountainde. And what happened
is for the next couple of months I ended
up losing everything. I could not get
anyone to invest in the idea. I burned
through the 30 grand that I borrowed
from my dad and I found myself homeless.
I had a couple hundred dollar in my bank
account and the only thing I could do to
make money was odd jobs and the only
place I could afford to rent so I wasn't
sleeping on the streets was a couch that
I rented for 200 bucks a month from a
Berkeley college student in his cramped
little apartment. So I could not afford
my own apartment. I couldn't even afford
a bed. I had to go up to a Berkeley
college student who also needed money
and rent his couch. And it wasn't even a
three-seater couch. It was a two-seater
couch, so my legs dangled off the end.
On that couch was everything I owned.
That couch stank. That couch had a
yellow stain on it. And I never wanted
to know what that yellow stain was. I
kept a towel on that couch every night
before I went to bed cuz I did not want
that stain touching my body. But that's
how I had to live for months and months
and months as I sent my resume out to
every company that was hiring online on
job sites of that time like Craigslist
just waiting for someone to offer me a
job. And then I certainly get an email
that changed my life. Okay. Now, did you
notice what I did there? I spoke about
the stakes. I spoke about the lowest of
the low. And everything I said was true.
That story of the couch, I've shared
that story hundreds of times from stage.
That story of being near homeless, I've
shared that and it's real and people can
relate to it cuz especially in the
United States, so many people have been
kicked out of their home because they
couldn't afford rent. But that story is
what makes the next spa especially
powerful. So what I just shared there
were the stakes. It was the lowest of
the low. This is where you not just
connect with the audience and bring in
vulnerability and humility. Don't make
things up. All of you have some story
from your past, some moment of misery
that you can share that might help other
people navigate their pain. Okay? So,
your chaos is sometimes a gift. The
darkness that you go through can
sometimes be a gift because when you
overcome that darkness, you have a story
that could inspire and move other
people. I just gave you the stakes and
here are the rules of the stakes. Don't
just describe the situation, describe
how you're feeling. So, when I tell that
story, I often go deeper into the shame
I felt asking my dad for help. I'd lost
his money and I knew my dad, if he knew
that I was homeless, would have given me
money for rent, but I'd lost his initial
30K. I couldn't ask him. So, I lied to
my parents. They thought I actually had
a decent apartment. I did not. I was
sleeping on a freaking couch. When I
tell that, that creates another level to
that stake, another level of
vulnerability. Okay? So, describe the
shame, the guilt, the anger. Describe
it. And now you come to the pivot. So,
notice how I set up the pivot. And then
I got that email. Okay? So, the pivot is
the turn. It's the turn that changed the
story. My email was an invite to my
first job, a job through which I would
learn everything I needed to later start
my company. That's a whole different
story. Maybe we don't need to go there,
but the turn is that turning point.
Often in the turn is a lesson that is
baked in. So let me tell you the turn in
my story. I go on to talk about how I
got a job and I got this job in this
company in Silicon Valley and the
economy was so bad there was no base
salary. Basically I had to pick up the
phone, call lawyers and sell them on
software. I describe how my boss told
me, "By the way, we don't pay a base
salary because we have a hundred people
waiting for your job if you can't
succeed. So, all I'm going to do is
this. No benefits, no base salary, but
you get to keep 20% of whatever you
close." Now, I had no experience in
sales. I was a computer scientist. And
for the first one month, I made
precisely zero sales. Now, I was working
a 50our week and getting [clears throat]
zero money. That was frightening cuz I
could not see any way out. Now, at this
point, I bring in the turn. It was 2001.
Now, Google had just come out and Google
was kind of a magical thing back then. I
remember getting on Google and typing
in, "Google, why does my life suck so
bad?" Or, "Google, why am I so pathetic?
Google, why am I such a loser?" Now,
notice what I did. I certainly ran from
the darkness, okay? The unfairness of my
employment, no base salary. I made it
lighter. I brought in a little bit of
humor cuz I'm making the turn. Okay, now
we're going to continue. When I put in
that request on Google, I saw a class.
The class was called Silva Ultramind. It
was a meditation class and they sit on
their web page that they would teach you
mindset. They would teach you how to
visualize your goals. They would even
teach you intuition, which they say is a
very human skill. You can tap into your
intuition and get a gut read on
situations. I was desperate. I took the
few hundred dollars I had, got a $100
flight to LA, attended the class, got
back on the plane the next day, flew
back to San Francisco to start my job,
and this is what happened. So, you see,
back then, we used the yellow pages. We
would go to the San Francisco Public
Library, check out the yellow pages, and
I had to call everyone in San Antonio.
All the people who are on the phone, we
had to call names from A to Z. But I'd
learned something cool through Silva
Ultramine. I learned how to close my
eyes and go into a meditative level of
mind and listen to my heart and
intuition. I would then run my finger
down the book and listen for an impulse.
Yes or no? Yes or no? I didn't know it
back then, but I was applying techniques
that many great CEOs say truly help with
decision-making. Steve Jobs in his
famous commencement address at Stanford
said,
>> "And most important, have the courage to
follow your heart and intuition. They
somehow already know what you truly want
to become. Everything else is secondary.
>> Professor John Mihalaski at Newark
College of Engineering, well, he did a
study and showed that CEOs and founders
who use intuition actually generate more
revenue for their company without
knowing it. I was using that technique.
I started just calling the names that
created this feeling of yes. And
overnight, my sales doubled. Every
single one of these crazy targets I
started hitting. I ended up getting four
promotions in three months and I was
made VP of sales. Now the funny thing is
this. I remember this day so vividly. I
was sitting at my desk and my boss comes
up to me. My boss was this Russian guy,
very very very brilliant mind, respected
him tremendously and he pounded on my
desk with a big smile on his face and he
said, "Bishan, what are you doing? This
is crazy. How are you closing so many
sales?" And I said, "I don't know, but I
think it's called intuition." And my
boss looked at me with a funny look on
his face. He dropped his shoulders and
he said, "Now that's but keep
doing it. And can you teach the rest of
us?" Now, notice what I did there. The
turn is where you share the discovery
that moved you. The discovery that you
want to get the audience to focus on. In
my speeches, I frequently speak about
intuition and the power of the mind. So,
my turn is getting the audience to now
open up their awareness to mindset and
intuition. That is how you do the turn.
The reason I love the concept of the
turn is that it brings a moment of
levity. It brings a moment of joy to the
scene. You have taken them through the
stakes into your darkest moment and now
you're bringing them out with you. And
this is a really powerful part of
storytelling. So the technique you're
learning is called holy That's so
smart. It's a technique for captivating
storytelling. Holy is the hook. is
stakes. That is the turn. And now we go
on to so which will remind you of the
word scene. So this is where many people
trip up. Their story is good. The turn
is good. But they forget to bring in the
scene. The scene is where you make
something visualizable. The audience can
be there in the moment with you. So I've
already been crafting the scene. Notice
the story of my boss. That's the scene.
You're bringing in humor. You're
bringing in something they can
visualize. Now, you can amplify the
scene. You can paint the picture and
make it richer. Human beings love that.
They love it when you describe the
weather, the carpet, the living room.
You can see yourself in that scene,
right? Notice pounded the table. I used
the hand gestures of my boss. I tried
with the best of my ability to describe
the puzzle look on his face. That is
expanding the scene. Many people rush
through a story. Stop doing that. Take
your time. Build a scene. The tiny
details, we often think they're
unimportant, but to an audience, you
bring the audience into the moment.
Okay. So, now we go on to the fifth
ingredient of your story, and that is
the shatter. The shatter is called
shatter because you're literally taking
an outdated belief and punching through
it. You're shattering the glass ceiling.
You're punching through whatever blocks
a person might believe they have. The
shatter is where you drop the lesson. So
what is the lesson of this story? It's
the lesson that Steve Jobs said in a
Stanford commencement address. Now when
I give this talk on stage, I talk about
how to access intuition. I talk about
altered states. I talk about meditation.
I talk about intuition principles. I
quote jobs. I quote scientific studies.
All of that is there. Yes. But the way
you design the shatter before you get to
all of the signs and all of the evidence
is to give people a single mic drop
moment. So the shatter comes with a mic
drop. This is the mic drop I use in my
story. That entire experience made me
understand one thing. For so much of my
life I was hustling. I was pushing. I
was struggling. overwork and I was
failing. But when I understood the
potential of the human mind, I realized
that sometimes the greatest secret of
success of all is to know how to sit
still and listen to that still gentle
voice within the voice of your
intuition. Did you see how that worked?
Now you want to know something crazy?
The Silver Ultram program changed my
life. And so as I started telling the
story, I ended up reaching out to the
the owners of that program, the creator
Jose Silva. He passed away in 1999. I
reached out to his children and I got
the rights to sell their CDs on a
website called that website Mind Value.
In 2018, the owners of the Silva program
asked me to recreate the program in my
storytelling style, in my voice for the
world. We published it, Silva Ultramind.
It's available on the Mind Valley app.
But here's the crazy thing. Because of
the storytelling that I brought in, that
course went on to become one of the
bestselling courses in the world. 40
million a year in revenue. The Silva
organization was incredibly happy. I was
happy because I got to teach something I
was really passionate about. And by the
way, it's now been 9 years since I
published the course. It is still the
number one program on Mindbaru. The way
I was able to make the course so popular
is bringing in storytelling as I teach
Jose Silva's principles of mindset but
also bringing in storytelling when I am
creating webinars to teach people about
the program. My webinars went on to get
millions upon millions of views on
YouTube and introduce millions of people
into Silva Ultram. See the power of
storytelling. So your story even if it's
a story of something you learned from
someone else. In my case, it was a story
of what I learned from Jose Silva. If
you can bring storytelling to a
principle, you get to take this idea and
expand it to a massive audience. If you
watch how I did this training and if you
watch it again, you will see as you went
through this training, I applied these
five things. Go back and watch the first
10 seconds of how we start this video.
And then I brought in the stakes. I
literally told you about my time almost
being homeless. There were multiple
turns in this. The turn of my book
hitting number one on Amazon. The turn
of discovering intuition. I painted
scenes many different times. The scene
of pounding vodka as I was about to get
on stage with the Dalai Lama. The scene
of my boss coming up to me. And then I
now bring in the mic drop. And this is
the mic drop moment I want you to know.
This is what I want you to remember.
Nobody changes their life because of a
fact. People changed their life because
they heard a story that give them hope
for who they could become. That is a mic
drop moment. And what you want to do is
come up with a mic drop sentence like
that to end your story. That's how you
make an impact. So let's recap. Holy
that's so smart. The hook, the
stakes, the turn, the scene, and the
shatter. Now, if one of these things are
missing, what happens is you can still
get a good story, but your story might
not make the impact that it needs to
make to truly land. For example, if you
miss out the stakes, you might come
across as being too arrogant. You might
come across as being unrelatable. If you
miss out the turn, but you have a really
good stake, you leave the audience sad,
wondering, "Oh my god, that's crazy.
That's awful." Now, the audience has a
bad, bad memory. If you leave out the
scene, you can have an incredible turn,
incredible stakes, but did the audience
really go there with you? If you leave
out the shatter, well, what's the point?
What are they meant to learn? Every
single one of these five points has a
purpose. If you're really trying to
capture an audience, you need to create
relatability and respect. You cannot
just have one. You can be relatable by
talking about, you know, stuff you're
going through and and you can be humble
and that makes you relatable. The
audience may like you, but are they
going to respect you? Are they going to
listen to you? You need relatability and
you need respect. When you start your
story, your hook, your stakes can give
you relatability, but your turn painting
the scene, the shatter, that can help
build respect because they see you as
someone who can convey a powerful,
life-changing idea or product. Stay with
me, click follow, add a comment. I'd
love to know your thoughts on this
video. I really want to do my best to
serve you. What else can I teach?
Because I'm going to try to teach one
thing every week, okay? And share this
with a friend, a friend who's speaking,
a friend who needs to share their
business idea. And I want you to know
I've also created a second video going
deeper in this method where I'm going to
expand on how to make your hook even
better. Expand on the stakes, expand on
the turn, expand on the scene, and
expand on the shatter. All right. So,
stay tuned and I'll see you in the next